Guide to the Constance M. Green papers, Undated
Special Collections Research Center, The Gelman Library, The George Washington University
Constance M. Green papers, undated
Green, Constance M.
MS2118
1 Linear feet
Collection primarily contains notes and early drafts of Constance Green's writings, and also includes pamphlets, bibliographies, and classroom materials in the area of urban and negro studies.
The George Washington University, The Gelman Library, Special Collections Research Center 2130 H. St. NW Washington, D.C. 20052 Phone: 202-994-7549 Email:
Information for Users
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
[required]
Historical or Biographical Note
Constance McLaughlin Green (1897-1975) was an accomplished historian and author of many scholarly books about urban history in the United States. Green was director of the Washington History Project at American University and an active member of the Committee of 100 on the Federal City. She won the 1963 Pulitzer Prize in history for the first volume of her study of Washington, D.C., "Washington: Village and Capital, 1800-1878."
Collection Scope and Content
This collection primarily contains notes and early drafts of Green's writings, and also includes pamphlets, bibliographies, and classroom materials in the area of urban and negro studies.
Collection Organization
Organized in five series: Notes to "The Secret City," Pamphlets and bibliographies on urban and negro studies, Class materials and student essays from the course "Negro Life in American Cities since 1860," Typescripts of later writings including "The Church on Lafayette Square," and Early drafts of "Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950."
Subject Terms
Individuals
Green, Constance McLaughlin
Corporate Entities
Topics
Constance M. Green collection; Washington (D.C.) history; Cities and towns Study and teaching; Black studies; African Americans Study and teaching
Geographic Locations
Washington (D.C.)
Detailed Description of the Records
- Notes to "The Secret City", undated, MS2118 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains notes taken by Constance Green in the preparation of "The Secret City."
  - Notes to "The Secret City", undated (Box 1)
  - Bibliographical information and notes taken from The History of The Bethel Literary and Historical Association and Negro Thought in America 1880-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Red, White and Black: Minority in America", 1969, a selected list of bibliographies published in 1969 by the American Library Association Conference. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes on the integration of D.C. Fire Departments, undated, from 1949-1962, used on pages 316-18 of Secret City, largely illegible. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Preliminary chronological notes concerning the governments role in racial relations and related issues, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Primarily notes concerning court records and trials, infringements of racial' laws, 1860's and 70's, undated, some census records and lists of courses and workshops on Minority Studies in the 1930's and 40's. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes about legislation and court cases concerning school budceting, integration, and related topics, undated, faculty, percentage of Negro students and teachers, and related topics. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes about Boy's Clubs, Fraternities, Parks and Playgrounds, and other recreational facilities, undated, in the district. Cryptic and often seemingly incoherent. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes taken at the Library of Congress on various subjects, undated, Mostly taken on scrap paper and difficult to decipher. These materials were not originally grouped together by the author. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Corrections of the typescript of a chapter entitled "Disillusionment and Readjustments", undated, includes scattered and illegible personal notes. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bibliography of Civil Rights and the Truman Administration, 02/1968, from the Harry S. Truman Library in Independence, Missouri. Feb. 1968. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes police court records and from other works., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes concerning schooling in the district with related court cases., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photocopied type-text of "Summary of an Era", undated, dealing with turn of the century Washington. Some hand¬written corrections. Authorship unknown. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photocopied typescript of "The Enforcement of the Civil Rights Act of 1875" by John Hope Franklin, 1966, December 1964. 26 pages with 5 pages of notes. (published in AHA 1966) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Pamphlets and bibliographies on urban and negro studies, undated, MS2118 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains pamphlets, essays, and bibliographies in the area of urban and negro studies.
  - Pamphlets and Bibliographies: Urban and Negro Studies, undated (Box 1)
  - "Black Studies" Myths and Realities, A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, 1969, September 1969. Including two loose newspaper articles: "Black Students Wont Yield" November 23, 1969 by Benjamin Fine. "For Good Schools Try Live Politics" by Richardson Dilworth. Both of unknown source. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Organization of American Historians Sixtieth Annual N.eeting.", 04/1967, Chicago, Ill. April 27-29, 1967. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Map of D.C. Area showing the spread of Negroes, 01/10/1964, who moved into previously all white areas- in an attempt to create equal housing opportunities. Metropolitain Washington Housing Program, American Friends Service Committee, Inc. October 1, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the history of women in America 1966-1968, undated, (Radcliffe College) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Three Essays by Bayard Rustin, 09/1969, Myths of the Black Revolt, The Role of the Negro Middle Class, The Ballot Box and Union Card. A. Philip Randolph Institute, September 1969. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Separatism of Integration- Which Way for America?" a dialogue by Robert S. Brown and Bayard Rustin, 10/1968, with an introduction by john A. Morsell. A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, October 1968. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Our Nation's Capital: The City and The Freeway" A symposium, 05/23/1965, May 23, 1965, State Department Auditorium, Wash. D.C. by the Committee on Urban Conservation. Mrs. Green was a participant and her remarks are recorded. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Complex Web, Problems and Prospects of the Contemporary Urban Scene", 1968-1969, a list of Praeger books on Urban Affairs. Winter 1968-69. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The City- A Bibliography of Current Classical Classical Readings", 1965, 2 pages. The Rise of Urban America by Mrs. Green is under fined in red. N.Y., Harper and Row, 1965. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Urban History Group" (Newsletter), 04/1966, Charles N. Glaab, editor. #21 April 1966. Mostly bibliographical material. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Report of the Institute on Minority Groups in an Urban Society", 08/1968, August 5-9, 1968. Montgomery County Public Schools. Rockville, Maryland. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Negro History and Literature" a selected bibliography, 12/1968, St. Clair Drake, professor of sociology at Roosevelt U., Chicago. National Federation of Settlements and Neighborhood Centers. December 1968. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "1972 Annual Report" Planned Parenthood of Metropolitain 6 Washington, 1972, Mailed to Mrs. Green. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Class materials and student essays from the course "Negro Life in American Cities since 1860", 1969, MS2118 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains notes, bibliographical material, and student essays from the class "Negro Life in American Cities Since 1860," taught by Constance Green at the George Washington University in the summer of 1969.
  - "Negro Life in American Cities Since 1860", undated (Box 1)
  - "The Urban Negro American In The 20th Century" and class discussion notes., undated, A survey of sources. Bibliographical material on diverse topics within the subject. Organization and comments of unknown authorship. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Students Essays. 14, including grades given., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typescripts of later writings including "The Church on Lafayette Square", undated, MS2118 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains typescripts of an essay titled "Urbanization, Technology, and the Historian" and a book titled "The Church on Lafayette Square: A History of St. John's Church, Washington, D.C.," both by Constance Green.
  - Typescripts of Late Writings, undated (Box 1)
  - "Urbanization, Technology anf The Historian" typescript, undated, This paper focusus on the historian's role in evaluating and researching the process of city-building,and its connection with the growth of technology. She discusses the state of research in the field of urban evolution as it was in the 1960's, and the approaches of several historians. Valuable insight into the needs of further study is given, along with extensive notes and bibliographical material. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescript, The Church on Lafayette Square: A History of St.John's Church, Wash.,D.C., undated, incomplete typescript by Constance McLaughlin Green. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Early drafts of "Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950", undated, MS2118 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains early drafts of what would become chapters 7, 8, 9, 15, 20, and unmarked chapters in "Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950," by Constance Green.
  - "Washington, Capital City, 1879 - 1950," Early Drafts with copies and corrections., undated (Box 2)
  - Drafts of Chapter 7, "Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950", undated, early draughts here marked Chapter 16. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Drafts of Chapter 8, "Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Draft, Part III, "From Uncertainty to Complaceny, 1878 - 1817", Chapter XI, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 9, Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unknown chapter, Capital City, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 15., undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 20., undated (Box 2, Folder 7)